There are people living in almost every corner of our crowded planet.
在我们这个拥挤的星球上，几乎每个角落都有人居住。
From the tops of mountains to deep underground, we’ve always been able to find habitable places to make a home.
从高山之巅到地下深处，人类总能找到适宜居住的地方安家落户。
But with space at a premium, we’ve started to look even deeper for somewhere to live.
但随着空间愈发稀缺，我们开始将目光投向更深的地方，寻找新的栖身之所。
Throughout history, people have been fascinated by the idea of living underwater.
自古以来，人类就对水下居住的构想十分着迷。
More recently, the effects of human activity on the land have led some to look to the oceans for natural resources.
近年来，人类活动对陆地造成的影响，让一些人开始将目光投向海洋，挖掘其中的自然资源。
Oceanographers and architects have looked at designing vessels, labs and underwater habitats to enable people to live and work in a submerged world.
海洋学家和建筑师们着手设计潜水器、实验室以及水下栖息地，希望能让人们在水下世界生活和工作。
But, while dreams of an aquatic city have remained a fantasy, how close are we to making our home on the seabed a reality?
不过，尽管水上城市的梦想至今仍停留在幻想阶段，但我们距离在海床安家落户的现实还有多远呢？
The pioneer of undersea living was Ian Koblick, sometimes described as an ‘aquanaut’.
水下居住的先驱者是伊恩·科布利克，他有时也被称为“海底居民”。
He claimed technology already existed to create underwater colonies supporting up to a hundred people.
他声称，现有的技术已经能够建造可容纳上百人的水下聚居地。
He even opened La Chalupa, once the largest and most advanced underwater habitat and research facility in the world.
他还曾创办了“拉查鲁帕”水下基地，这里一度是全球规模最大、技术最先进的水下栖息地与研究设施。
A more recent and ambitious design for an underwater city is Ocean Spiral.
“海洋螺旋”是近年来一个更为宏大的水下城市设计方案。
Designed by the Japanese Shimizu Corporation, it’s a huge transparent globe attached to the seabed.
这个方案由日本清水建设株式会社设计，主体是一个固定在海床上的巨大透明球体。
It’s got a tower running through it to the surface, providing space for homes, offices and even an amusement park for five thousand residents.
球体内有一座贯穿上下、直达海面的塔楼，可为五千名居民提供住宅、办公区域，甚至还有一座游乐园。
Masaki Takeuchi from the company told the BBC: “Our idea is to connect the sea surface and the deep sea vertically, and that way we believe that we can utilise the capability of the deep sea.”
该公司的竹内正树在接受BBC采访时表示：“我们的构想是将海面与深海垂直连接起来，我们相信通过这种方式，能够充分开发深海的潜在价值。”
Of course, there are engineering challenges in constructing an oceanic metropolis.
当然，建造一座海洋大都市面临着诸多工程难题。
And living underwater would have major effects on the human body, especially as there is an increase in atmospheric pressure which could lead to the bends.
而且水下生活也会对人体产生重大影响，尤其是水下气压的升高可能会导致潜水员患上减压病。
So, maybe it’s too soon to be packing our bags and setting up a new life three thousand metres under the sea!
如此看来，现在就打包行李，去三千米深的海底开启新生活，或许还为时过早。